<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-09-19T15:59:08+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">PhD workshop (in person) Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning research and democracy – an</title><subtitle>an interdisciplinary perspective 29.1 – 31.1.2022 at the University of Tübingen</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Program and what to expect</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/HowCanWeUseMLfortheGood/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Program and what to expect" /><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/HowCanWeUseMLfortheGood</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/HowCanWeUseMLfortheGood/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hands.jpg&quot; style=&quot;zoom:80%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katharina Anderer</name></author><category term="AI" /><category term="democracy" /><category term="ethics" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why we need to think more about people’s preferences with regard to sustainable mobility concepts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Mobility_concepts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why we need to think more about people’s preferences with regard to sustainable mobility concepts" /><published>2021-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Mobility_concepts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Mobility_concepts/">&lt;p&gt;When we discuss about mobility solutions for the future, we should not only consider a comparison of emission values of different transport systems. What is often not included in the debate, are user preferences and predictions about people’s change in behavior. Autonomous self-driving cars might reduce emissions by allowing a better traffic flow, compared to the same number of conventional cars on the street. But the contribution of self-driving cars to sustainable mobility is more than dubious if private cars remain the preferred travel mode. There could even be an increase in people’s preferences for private cars when autonomous cars become one of the most comfortable and time-efficient travel modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question is whether or not autonomous self-driving cars can be regarded as future vehicles. We need attractive systems that shift people’s preferences towards public and emission-friendly transport systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unintended-effects-of-autonomous-driving&quot;&gt;Unintended Effects of Autonomous Driving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakusch, Stevens, Boden and Bossauer (2018) conducted an online survey that suggested that the ownership of a private car will remain popular in the future. What is alarming as well is that the growth of carsharing will mostly by at the expense of public transport. So even that an increasing number of people use carsharing offers, these people were using public transports in the past. A concept such as carsharing that seems to be sustainable at first glance, can have the opposite effect as intended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors of the article investigated the migration of user preferences for the hypothetical scenario of autonomous vehicles and autonomous carsharing being available. Their alarming result of the survey was that private cars would not diminish, but carsharing usage would increase  at the expense of a reduction in the usage of public transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;involving-people&quot;&gt;Involving people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their paper, Sopjani et al. (2019), describe that a transition to low-carbon mobility should not only look for innovative design, but it is also important to search for approaches that motivates users to change their travel practices. They argue that a critical mass is necessary to give momentum to a new innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new technology like e-buses might only be successful if a lot of people can be motivated to use them instead of using their own cars. If it leads only to more users that would have used an even more sustainable transport vehicle before, such as a bike, it might not bring the intended effect of lowering the carbon emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;smart-solutions&quot;&gt;Smart solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some “smart” ideas for modern, low-carbon mobility systems are summarized by the project “GoSmarter” &lt;a href=&quot;https://grow-smarter.eu/fileadmin/editor-upload/Smart/Action_Area_3-compressed.pdf&quot;&gt;GrowSmarter link&lt;/a&gt;. These include neighbourhood parcel delivery rooms, travel demand management apps, a charging infrastructure for e-vehicles or a traffic signal priority for heavy duty vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A parcel delivery room is a concept developed in the city of Stockholm that uses e.g. some room of the bottom floor of a multistorey house as delivery room. It has the idea to reduce delivery traffic. The parcels are delivered by e-cargo bikes and every user can access the delivery room any time using a smartphone app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traffic management tools, on the other side, could help to assist with a better traffic flow, avoiding that more vehicles are navigated through congested areas. If you now think - well, my google navigation already helps me with that - you are right to a certain extend, but these traffic management tools would not choose a navigation route with respect to the best time or road preferences, but rather use air quality as a measure to avoid certain routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A traffic signal priority aims at reducing the number of starts and stops of heavy vehicles, which should reduce the pollution impact of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-thoughts&quot;&gt;Further thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For mobility concepts we cannot just divide mobility technologies into good and evil, high-emission and low-emission vehicles and so on. Every city, every region can be different because of the already installed infrastructure, but most of all because of the people that live there. To engage people in making sustainable mobility choices, we need to involve them in the transition processes, ask them about their needs and preferences, make them an important part of the change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakusch, C., Stevens, G., Boden, A.,  &amp;amp; Bossauer, P. (2018). Unintended effects of autonomous driving: A  study on mobility preferences in the future. &lt;em&gt;Sustainability&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;10&lt;/em&gt;(7), 2404.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sopjani, L., Stier, J. J., Ritzén, S., Hesselgren, M., &amp;amp; Georén, P. (2019). Involving users and user roles in the transition to sustainable mobility systems: The case of light  electric vehicle sharing in Sweden. &lt;em&gt;Transportation Research Part D: Transport and Environment&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;71&lt;/em&gt;, 207-221.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://grow-smarter.eu/fileadmin/editor-upload/Smart/Action_Area_3-compressed.pdf&quot;&gt;GrowSmarter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Katharina Anderer</name></author><category term="AI" /><category term="machine learning" /><category term="autonomous driving" /><category term="e-mobility" /><category term="locality" /><category term="mobility" /><summary type="html">When we discuss about mobility solutions for the future, we should not only consider a comparison of emission values of different transport systems. What is often not included in the debate, are user preferences and predictions about people’s change in behavior. Autonomous self-driving cars might reduce emissions by allowing a better traffic flow, compared to the same number of conventional cars on the street. But the contribution of self-driving cars to sustainable mobility is more than dubious if private cars remain the preferred travel mode. There could even be an increase in people’s preferences for private cars when autonomous cars become one of the most comfortable and time-efficient travel modes.</summary></entry></feed>